Good morning. How are you?
早上好，还好吗? 很好吧，对不对?
(Audience) Good.
It's been great, hasn't it?
早上好，还好吗? 很好吧，对不对?
I've been blown away by the whole thing.
我已经飘飘然了!
In fact, I'm leaving.
(Laughter)
我要飘走了。(笑声)
There have been three themes running through the conference,
这次会议有三个主题
which are relevant to what I want to talk about.
这三个主题贯穿会议始终，并且和
One is the extraordinary evidence of human creativity
我要谈的内容有关
in all of the presentations that we've had
其中之一就是人类创造力的伟大例证
and in all of the people here;
这些例证已经体现在之前的演讲当中
just the variety of it and the range of it.
以及在座各位的身上。 从这些例证中我们看到了创新的多样化
The second is that it's put us in a place
和多领域。第二点--
where we have no idea what's going to happen
这些创新也让我们意识到 我们不知道未来会发生什么
in terms of the future.
No idea how this may play out.
完全不知道
I have an interest in education.
我对教育感兴趣
Actually, what I find is, everybody has an interest in education.
Don't you?
难道不是吗? 我发现这很有趣
I find this very interesting.
If you're at a dinner party, and you say you work in education --
如果你参加一个晚宴，你说
actually, you're not often at dinner parties, frankly.
你在教育部门工作
(Laughter)
坦白的讲，如果你在教育部门工作， 事实上你不会经常参加晚宴，
If you work in education, you're not asked.
(Laughter)
(笑声) 所以你不会被问及你是做哪行的。
And you're never asked back, curiously. That's strange to me.
你永远不会被问到，很奇怪。
But if you are, and you say to somebody,
但是如果你被问及，
you know, they say, "What do you do?"
他们问:"你从事什么行业?"
and you say you work in education,
你说你在教育部门工作
you can see the blood run from their face.
你会发现他们涨红了脸，那意思好像是
They're like, "Oh my God. Why me?"
(Laughter)
你会发现他们涨红了脸，那意思好像是
"My one night out all week."
“我的天啊，” “为什么让我碰上？ 整整一周我才出来一次” (笑声)
(Laughter)
But if you ask about their education, they pin you to the wall,
但如果你要他们谈谈他们的受教育经历，
because it's one of those things that goes deep with people, am I right?
他们会把你“钉到墙上”。 因为这些事情都涉及
Like religion and money and other things.
比如宗教信仰,薪水等
So I have a big interest in education, and I think we all do.
我对教育特别感兴趣， 我认为我们都是如此
We have a huge vested interest in it,
我们对此有巨大的既得利益
partly because it's education that's meant to take us into this future
部分因为教育旨在
that we can't grasp.
将我们带入我们无法掌握的未来
If you think of it,
children starting school this year will be retiring in 2065.
大家想想，今年入学的小孩
despite all the expertise that's been on parade for the past four days,
虽然过去四天会议进程里 都是关于这方面的专业讨论--
what the world will look like in five years' time.
但我们还是无法预知这个世界
And yet, we're meant to be educating them for it.
五年后的样子。 这就是为何我们要让这些孩子
So the unpredictability, I think, is extraordinary.
接受教育。我认为正是未来的不确定性
And the third part of this is that we've all agreed, nonetheless,
决定其非同寻常。
on the really extraordinary capacities that children have --
我们都认同一个观点--
their capacities for innovation.
这些孩子的特别之处正是
I mean, Sirena last night was a marvel, wasn't she?
他们的创新能力。我觉得昨晚 Sirena 的表现令人惊奇，
Just seeing what she could do.
对吗？
And she's exceptional, but I think she's not, so to speak,
她很出色，但是我认为
exceptional in the whole of childhood.
她在孩提时代时没显得与众不同。
What you have there is a person of extraordinary dedication
现在的教育提倡的是 一个有奉献精神的老师
who found a talent.
能发现一个天才学生。但我认为
And my contention is, all kids have tremendous talents,
所有孩子都是伟大的天才。
and we squander them, pretty ruthlessly.
而我们却无情地扼杀了他们的才能。
So I want to talk about education,
所以我想谈谈教育和
and I want to talk about creativity.
My contention is that creativity now is as important in education as literacy,
创造力。我认为
and we should treat it with the same status.
所以这两方面我们应同等对待。
(Applause)
（掌声）谢谢。而且，
Thank you.
(Applause)
（掌声）谢谢。而且，
That was it, by the way. Thank you very much.
(Laughter)
非常感谢。（笑声）还剩15分钟。
So, 15 minutes left.
(Laughter)
我出生于--说错了（笑声）
"Well, I was born ... "
(Laughter)
我出生于--说错了（笑声）
I heard a great story recently -- I love telling it --
最近我听到一个很不错的故事 --我很愿意讲讲这个故事--
of a little girl who was in a drawing lesson.
说的是一个小女孩正在上绘画课。 小女孩只有六岁
She was six, and she was at the back, drawing,
她坐在教室的后排，正在画画，
and the teacher said this girl hardly ever paid attention,
而她的老师评价她几乎从不
and in this drawing lesson, she did.
注意听讲，但在绘画课上她却听得很认真。
The teacher was fascinated.
She went over to her, and she said, "What are you drawing?"
老师饶有兴趣地走过去
And the girl said, "I'm drawing a picture of God."
问她：“你在画什么？”
And the teacher said, "But nobody knows what God looks like."
她说：“我画的是上帝。”
And the girl said, "They will in a minute."
老师说：“可是没人知道上帝长什么样。”
(Laughter)
这时小女孩说： “他们马上就能知道上帝的样子了。”
When my son was four in England --
我儿子四岁时在英国--
actually, he was four everywhere, to be honest.
实际上他那会儿在哪都四岁（笑声）
(Laughter)
严格地说他四岁那年在哪个国家记不清了， 只记得他四岁那年
If we're being strict about it, wherever he went, he was four that year.
He was in the Nativity play. Do you remember the story?
去演舞台剧《基督诞生》
(Laughter)
你们记得那部剧的情节吗？ 应该记不得，情节太长。
No, it was big, it was a big story.
Mel Gibson did the sequel, you may have seen it.
故事太长。梅尔.吉布森演过那部剧的续集。
(Laughter)
你们也许看过，叫《基督诞生II》。 我儿子 James 在那部舞台剧里演 Joseph，
"Nativity II."
But James got the part of Joseph, which we were thrilled about.
你们也许看过，叫《基督诞生II》。 我儿子 James 在那部舞台剧里演 Joseph，
We considered this to be one of the lead parts.
我们为此很兴奋。
We had the place crammed full of agents in T-shirts:
我们给观众们发了T恤：
"James Robinson IS Joseph!"
上面印着 “James Robinson 扮演 Joseph" (笑声）
(Laughter)
He didn't have to speak, but you know the bit where the three kings come in?
他的角色不一定有台词，剧情是
They come in bearing gifts, gold, frankincense and myrrh.
三个国王拿着礼物走进来
This really happened.
他们分别拿着黄金，乳香精油，没药精油。
We were sitting there, and I think they just went out of sequence,
演出开始了。我们坐在观众席上
because we talked to the little boy afterward and said,
演出结束后我们对James说：
"You OK with that?" They said, "Yeah, why? Was that wrong?"
“你们刚才演的对吗？” 他说：“对啊，怎么了，哪错了吗？”
They just switched.
其实他们把剧情改了。
The three boys came in, four-year-olds with tea towels on their heads.
他们是这么演的：三个小演员出场，
They put these boxes down, and the first boy said, "I bring you gold."
他们放下手上拿的盒子
And the second boy said, "I bring you myrrh."
第一个孩子说：“我带来了黄金。”
And the third boy said, "Frank sent this."
第二个孩子说：“我带来了没药精油。”
(Laughter)
第三个孩子说： “Frank带来了这个”（笑声）
What these things have in common is that kids will take a chance.
If they don't know, they'll have a go.
对于未知的事物，他们愿意去尝试。
Am I right? They're not frightened of being wrong.
难道不是吗？ 即使尝试的结果是错误的，他们也不惧怕。
I don't mean to say that being wrong is the same thing as being creative.
当然，我并不认为错误的尝试等同于创新。
What we do know is, if you're not prepared to be wrong,
但我们都知道
you'll never come up with anything original --
如果你不打算做错误的尝试
if you're not prepared to be wrong.
你永远不会创造出新东西。
And by the time they get to be adults, most kids have lost that capacity.
如果你不想让孩子们做错误的尝试， 等他们长大了，
They have become frightened of being wrong.
那就会使他们也变得惧怕错误的尝试。
And we run our companies like this.
这种情况也存在于公司经营方面。
We stigmatize mistakes.
我们不能容忍任何错误。 这就使得现在的
And we're now running national education systems
where mistakes are the worst thing you can make.
教育体系成为
And the result is that we are educating people
最不能容忍错误的领域。
out of their creative capacities.
这样做的后果就是 我们的教育体制正在扼杀
Picasso once said this, he said that all children are born artists.
孩子们的创造力。毕加索曾说过:
The problem is to remain an artist as we grow up.
“孩子们是天生的艺术家”
I believe this passionately, that we don't grow into creativity,
问题是我们长大后 能否继续保有艺术灵感。我坚信：
we grow out of it.
甚至可以说，是我们所受的教育 让我们丧失了创造力。
Or rather, we get educated out of it.
So why is this?
为什么会这样？
I lived in Stratford-on-Avon until about five years ago.
五年前，我住在Stratford-on-Avon。
In fact, we moved from Stratford to Los Angeles.
现在我已经搬到了洛杉矶。
So you can imagine what a seamless transition this was.
可想而知，这是个多么合乎逻辑的移居。
(Laughter)
（笑声）其实，
Actually, we lived in a place called Snitterfield,
just outside Stratford,
就在 Stratford 郊外，那里是
which is where Shakespeare's father was born.
Are you struck by a new thought? I was.
莎士比亚父亲的出生地。 你有过灵感吗？我曾经有过。
You don't think of Shakespeare having a father, do you?
Do you?
因为你忽略了
Because you don't think of Shakespeare being a child, do you?
Shakespeare being seven?
莎士比亚七岁时什么样？ 我从没想过--他七岁时
I never thought of it.
I mean, he was seven at some point.
莎士比亚七岁时什么样？ 我从没想过--他七岁时
He was in somebody's English class, wasn't he?
的某个特定场景。比如他在上
(Laughter)
英语课， 想想他在上英语课--多么不可思议
How annoying would that be?
(Laughter)
（笑声)“你要努力学习” 你能想象他父亲边说边把他抱上床，
"Must try harder."
(Laughter)
（笑声)“你要努力学习” 你能想象他父亲边说边把他抱上床，
Being sent to bed by his dad, to Shakespeare, "Go to bed, now!"
“现在该睡觉了”
To William Shakespeare.
他父亲又说：“放下笔，
"And put the pencil down!"
(Laughter)
别再写那些东西了，别人都看不懂。”
"And stop speaking like that."
(Laughter)
别再写那些东西了，别人都看不懂。”
"It's confusing everybody."
(Laughter)
（笑声）
Anyway, we moved from Stratford to Los Angeles,
话说远了，刚才说到我们从 Stratford 搬到洛杉矶，
and I just want to say a word about the transition.
我想说的是，对于这次搬家，
Actually, my son didn't want to come.
我儿子并不愿意。
I've got two kids; he's 21 now, my daughter's 16.
我有两个孩子。 儿子现在21岁了，女儿16岁。
He didn't want to come to Los Angeles.
He loved it, but he had a girlfriend in England.
但在英国，他有个女友， 是他的最爱，叫 Sarah。
This was the love of his life, Sarah.
He'd known her for a month.
他们认识只有一个月后就开始交往了。
(Laughter)
我们要搬家时他们已交往了4年。
Mind you, they'd had their fourth anniversary,
because it's a long time when you're 16.
这对于16岁的年龄来说已经很长了。
He was really upset on the plane.
我儿子上了飞机后很郁闷，
He said, "I'll never find another girl like Sarah."
他说：“我再也找不到像 Sarah 那样的女孩了。”
And we were rather pleased about that, frankly --
但说实话， 做为家长的我们为此很庆幸。
(Laughter)
因为那个女孩是我们搬家的主要原因。
because she was the main reason we were leaving the country.
(Laughter)
（笑声）
But something strikes you when you move to America
如果你周游世界
and travel around the world:
你会发现每个国家的教育体系 都存在相同的学科等级制度。
every education system on earth has the same hierarchy of subjects.
Every one. Doesn't matter where you go.
没有例外。不论哪个国家。
You'd think it would be otherwise, but it isn't.
你认为也许会有例外，但没有。
At the top are mathematics and languages, then the humanities.
排在最前面的学科是数学和语言，
At the bottom are the arts. Everywhere on earth.
接下去是人文学科，艺术排在最后。
And in pretty much every system, too, there's a hierarchy within the arts.
而且相同的还有
Art and music are normally given a higher status in schools
就是在艺术学科范围内也有等级制。
than drama and dance.
然后是戏剧课和舞蹈课。 没有哪个国家的教育体系
There isn't an education system on the planet
that teaches dance every day to children
天天安排舞蹈课
the way we teach them mathematics.
但却每天都安排数学课。为什么？
Why?
Why not?
为什么不是每天安排舞蹈课呢？ 我认为舞蹈课很重要。
I think this is rather important.
I think math is very important, but so is dance.
我认为舞蹈课和数学课同样重要。
Children dance all the time if they're allowed to, we all do.
如果有允许，孩子们会不停地跳舞， 我们也一样。
We all have bodies, don't we? Did I miss a meeting?
我们都有体会，对吗？
(Laughter)
（笑声）事实上，
Truthfully, what happens is, as children grow up,
we start to educate them progressively from the waist up.
随着孩子年龄增长，我们开始教导他们
And then we focus on their heads.
别的东西，（以前是教他们走和跑）， 而随着他们长大，我们更关注的是他们的头脑。
And slightly to one side.
而且略微偏重大脑的一侧。
If you were to visit education as an alien
如果你以一个外国人的身份来参观我们的教育体系，
and say "What's it for, public education?"
带着这样的问题：“公办教育的目的是什么？”
I think you'd have to conclude, if you look at the output,
那么当你看到我们的教育体系产业化的发展， 我相信，你就会明白
who really succeeds by this,
是谁在真正从中受益，
who does everything they should,
是谁被教导着该做什么不该做什么，
who gets all the brownie points, who are the winners --
I think you'd have to conclude the whole purpose of public education
是谁得了满分，谁是第一名--
throughout the world
世界上所有的公办教育
is to produce university professors.
都以培养大学教授为目的。难道不是吗？
Isn't it?
They're the people who come out the top.
都以培养大学教授为目的。难道不是吗？
And I used to be one, so there.
因为大学教授是象牙塔尖上的人。
(Laughter)
我也曾是一名大学教授， 也是塔尖上的人。（笑声）
And I like university professors,
我倾慕大学教授的学识，但
but, you know, we shouldn't hold them up
as the high-water mark of all human achievement.
我们不应该用这样一个头衔作为 衡量一个人成功与否的分水岭。
They're just a form of life.
Another form of life.
只不过他们比较好求知，
But they're rather curious.
And I say this out of affection for them:
我这样说不是因为对他们的倾慕。
there's something curious about professors.
在我看来，大学教授有个特点--
In my experience -- not all of them, but typically -- they live in their heads.
虽然不是共性，但很典型-- 他们只用脑子生活。
They live up there and slightly to one side.
而且偏重于大脑的一侧。
They're disembodied, you know, in a kind of literal way.
用书面语来说就是--他们脑体分离。
They look upon their body as a form of transport for their heads.
他们只是把身体当作
(Laughter)
大脑的载体而已，难道不是吗？
Don't they?
It's a way of getting their head to meetings.
（笑声)这个载体可以载着大脑去开会。
(Laughter)
If you want real evidence of out-of-body experiences, by the way,
如果你想亲身体验
get yourself along to a residential conference of senior academics
你就去参加一次会议
and pop into the discotheque on the final night.
然后在会议结束后再去迪厅蹦迪。
(Laughter)
And there, you will see it.
（笑声）在那你会看到，成年男女
Grown men and women writhing uncontrollably, off the beat.
(Laughter)
期待夜晚的结束好回家 写篇关于蹦迪的论文。
Waiting until it ends, so they can go home and write a paper about it.
(Laughter)
注重培养学术能力的观点根植于 我们的教育体系之中。
Our education system is predicated on the idea of academic ability.
And there's a reason.
形成这种状况还有个原因--
Around the world, there were no public systems of education,
所有国家的教育体系在最初建立时
really, before the 19th century.
也就是在19世纪之前-- 那时教育还不是公共事业。
They all came into being to meet the needs of industrialism.
那时建立教育体系
So the hierarchy is rooted on two ideas.
所以有两点基本的等级原则。
Number one, that the most useful subjects for work are at the top.
第一点，对工作最实用的科目
So you were probably steered benignly away from things at school
是最重要的科目。 这样就能轻易地避开
when you were a kid,
理由就是
things you liked,
on the grounds you would never get a job doing that.
不这样学就找不到工作。对吗？
Is that right?
"Don't do music, you're not going to be a musician;
别玩音乐了，你成不了音乐家；
don't do art, you won't be an artist."
别画画了，你成不了艺术家。
Benign advice -- now, profoundly mistaken.
这些温和的忠告-- 筑成现在的大错。全世界
The whole world is engulfed in a revolution.
And the second is academic ability,
第二点，学术能力已经成为
which has really come to dominate our view of intelligence,
because the universities design the system in their image.
这种标准是那些大学自己制定的。
If you think of it,
只要你思考一下就会发现整个教育体系
the whole system of public education around the world is a protracted process
不论哪个国家的公共教育 都是一种按部就班的程序
of university entrance.
最终目标是为了考入大学。
And the consequence is that many highly talented,
造成的后果就是许多很有天才的
brilliant, creative people think they're not,
有创造力的学生被钝化了。
because the thing they were good at at school
因为这些学生发现他们的专长在学校
wasn't valued, or was actually stigmatized.
并不受重视甚至还受到蔑视。
And I think we can't afford to go on that way.
In the next 30 years, according to UNESCO,
我认为我们不能再这样扼杀孩子们的天才了。
more people worldwide will be graduating through education
全世界毕业的学生将超过
than since the beginning of history.
过去的总和。
More people.
这就是人口增长造成的， 人口增长关系到
And it's the combination of all the things we've talked about:
technology and its transformational effect on work,
包括技术和技术变革 对生产力的影响、人口统计学
and demography and the huge explosion in population.
及人口爆炸。
Suddenly, degrees aren't worth anything.
很快，文凭就不再有含金量了。是这样吧？
Isn't that true?
我上学那会儿，有文凭就有工作。
When I was a student, if you had a degree, you had a job.
If you didn't have a job, it's because you didn't want one.
那时候如果你没工作，那是因为你不想找。
And I didn't want one, frankly.
说实话，我那时候就是这样。（笑声）
(Laughter)
但现在的状况是，孩子们有文凭却经常
But now kids with degrees are often heading home
to carry on playing video games,
呆在家里打电脑游戏，
because you need an MA where the previous job required a BA,
因为以前只要学士学位的工作岗位 现在需要硕士学位，
and now you need a PhD for the other.
现在还没毕业的孩子将来 就得有个博士学位才好找工作。
It's a process of academic inflation.
这就是学术学位的通货膨胀。
And it indicates the whole structure of education is shifting beneath our feet.
We need to radically rethink our view of intelligence.
坍塌的前兆。我们必须从根本上反思
We know three things about intelligence.
培养人才有三个原则
One, it's diverse.
第一，多样化。 我们认知世界的角度不同
We think about the world in all the ways that we experience it.
We think visually, we think in sound, we think kinesthetically.
有的从听觉角度，有的从美学角度
We think in abstract terms, we think in movement.
有的从抽象的角度， 有的从动态的角度。
Secondly, intelligence is dynamic.
If you look at the interactions of a human brain,
如果观察一下人类大脑的内部组织，就像我们
as we heard yesterday from a number of presentations,
intelligence is wonderfully interactive.
大脑发育具有关联性。
The brain isn't divided into compartments.
大脑不应被分成几部分。
In fact, creativity --
which I define as the process of having original ideas that have value --
其实我认为应该创造性地 把大脑看作一整套工序--
more often than not comes about
这种原创想法往往来自互动的思考方式
through the interaction of different disciplinary ways of seeing things.
By the way, there's a shaft of nerves that joins the two halves of the brain,
大脑本来就是
called the corpus callosum.
这个连接部分叫胼胝体（医学名词）。 女性大脑中的这个部分比男性的要厚。
It's thicker in women.
Following off from Helen yesterday,
昨天听了Helen的演讲受到启发，我认为
this is probably why women are better at multitasking.
脑部特征可能使女性更善于 应对头绪纷乱的事情。
Because you are, aren't you?
对吗？
There's a raft of research, but I know it from my personal life.
虽然关于这方面的研究有很多， 但我对于这方面的了解 其实来源于我的亲身体验。
If my wife is cooking a meal at home, which is not often ...
我妻子在家做饭时--
thankfully.
感谢上帝，她不常做饭，（笑声）
(Laughter)
虽然她不擅厨艺但很擅长其他一些事--
No, she's good at some things.
不过她做饭时总是
But if she's cooking, she's dealing with people on the phone,
she's talking to the kids, she's painting the ceiling --
和孩子们说说话，给天棚刷刷漆，
(Laughter)
还在旁边做开胸手术。
she's doing open-heart surgery over here.
If I'm cooking, the door is shut, the kids are out,
而我做饭时就会关上厨房门， 不让孩子们进来打扰，
the phone's on the hook,
不打电话，这时如果我妻子进来我会很生气。
if she comes in, I get annoyed.
I say, "Terry, please, I'm trying to fry an egg in here."
我会这样对我妻子说： “Terry，我在煎鸡蛋，请你别打扰。”（笑声）
(Laughter)
"Give me a break."
我会这样对我妻子说： “Terry，我在煎鸡蛋，请你别打扰。”（笑声）
(Laughter)
Actually, do you know that old philosophical thing,
大家都知道那句有哲理的话--
"If a tree falls in a forest, and nobody hears it, did it happen?"
如果森林里有棵树倒了可没人听到，
Remember that old chestnut?
那是否意味着没发生过？记得这句话吗？
I saw a great T-shirt recently, which said,
"If a man speaks his mind in a forest, and no woman hears him,
最近我看到一件很棒的T恤， 上面印着：“如果一个男人说出他的心声
is he still wrong?"
却是在森林里说的，而且没被女人听到，
(Laughter)
那应该不算犯错吧？”（笑声）
And the third thing about intelligence is,
培养好学生的第三个原则就是--
it's distinct.
个性化。我目前在写本书--
I'm doing a new book at the moment called "Epiphany,"
which is based on a series of interviews with people
书名叫《顿悟》，素材来自一些
about how they discovered their talent.
自身的才能。对于这点我很感兴趣。
I'm fascinated by how people got to be there.
It's really prompted by a conversation I had with a wonderful woman
激发我写这本书的原因是一次对话
who maybe most people have never heard of, Gillian Lynne.
没听说过这个人，她叫Gillian Lynne,
Have you heard of her? Some have.
你们知道这个人吗？应该有人知道吧。 她是一个舞蹈编剧
She's a choreographer, and everybody knows her work.
所有人都知道她的作品。
She did "Cats" and "Phantom of the Opera."
她编舞的作品有《猫》、《歌剧魅影》。
She's wonderful.
她很有才华。我在英国看过 由皇家芭蕾舞团演出的她的作品。
I used to be on the board of The Royal Ballet, as you can see.
(Laughter)
你们也看过她的作品。
Gillian and I had lunch one day. I said, "How did you get to be a dancer?"
有一次，我和Gillian 吃午饭，我问她：
It was interesting.
说起来很有意思，她上学的时候，
When she was at school, she was really hopeless.
觉得自己完全没有希望。 她上学那会儿是1930年代，
And the school, in the '30s, wrote to her parents and said,
"We think Gillian has a learning disorder."
Gillian患有学习障碍症。”她无法集中注意力，
She couldn't concentrate; she was fidgeting.
她老是坐不安生。 用现在的话讲，那意思就是
I think now they'd say she had ADHD.
她有多动症。你们也这么想吧？ 但那时候是1930年代，
Wouldn't you?
But this was the 1930s, and ADHD hadn't been invented at this point.
她有多动症。你们也这么想吧？ 但那时候是1930年代，
It wasn't an available condition.
那个老师用词不当。（笑声）
(Laughter)
People weren't aware they could have that.
那时候人们还不知道用“多动症”这个词。
(Laughter)
于是，Gillian去看病。
Anyway, she went to see this specialist.
So, this oak-paneled room, and she was there with her mother,
医生让她坐在椅子上，
and she was led and sat on this chair at the end,
她把手压在腿下，这样过了20分钟
and she sat on her hands for 20 minutes,
她妈妈一直在向医生讲述
while this man talked to her mother
Gillian在学校的表现：
about all the problems Gillian was having at school,
because she was disturbing people, her homework was always late, and so on.
她在学校不安生，
Little kid of eight.
其实不过是个才8岁的孩子--最后， 医生走过去坐到
In the end, the doctor went and sat next to Gillian and said,
"I've listened to all these things your mother's told me.
你妈妈跟我说了很多
I need to speak to her privately.
现在我想和你妈妈单独谈谈。”
Wait here. We'll be back. We won't be very long,"
“你在这儿等一下，我们马上谈完。”
and they went and left her.
医生和她妈妈出去了。
But as they went out of the room,
但医生在出去时把收音机打开了
he turned on the radio that was sitting on his desk.
收音机在医生办公桌上。在他们
And when they got out of the room,
走出房间后，医生对她妈妈说:
he said to her mother, "Just stand and watch her."
“我们就站在这儿观察一下她。 ”他们离开房间后，
And the minute they left the room,
Gillian站起来，随着音乐跳起舞来。
she was on her feet, moving to the music.
And they watched for a few minutes, and he turned to her mother and said,
她妈妈和医生在门外看了几分钟
"Mrs. Lynne, Gillian isn't sick.
Lynne太太，Gillian没病， 她是个舞蹈天才。
She's a dancer.
Take her to a dance school."
让她去上舞蹈学校吧。”
I said, "What happened?"
话说到这，我问Gillian：“后来怎么样了？”
She said, "She did. I can't tell you how wonderful it was.
We walked in this room, and it was full of people like me --
她回答道：“我妈妈送我去了舞蹈学校。 我无法形容那里有多棒。
people who couldn't sit still,
像我这样的人--坐不住的人。
people who had to move to think."
我们必须在动态中才能思考。”
Who had to move to think.
他们跳芭蕾，跳踢踏舞，跳爵士舞，
They did ballet, they did tap, jazz; they did modern; they did contemporary.
She was eventually auditioned for the Royal Ballet School.
后来她考入皇家芭蕾舞学校，
She became a soloist; she had a wonderful career at the Royal Ballet.
成为芭蕾舞女主演，事业发展很成功
She eventually graduated from the Royal Ballet School,
从皇家芭蕾舞学校毕业后
founded the Gillian Lynne Dance Company,
她成立了自己的公司 --Gillian Lynne 舞蹈公司
met Andrew Lloyd Webber.
遇到了Andrew Lloyd Weber （注：歌舞剧《猫》的编曲者）。她负责
She's been responsible for
some of the most successful musical theater productions in history,
遇到了Andrew Lloyd Weber （注：歌舞剧《猫》的编曲者）。她负责
she's given pleasure to millions,
她给数以万计的观众带来了艺术享受，
and she's a multimillionaire.
Somebody else might have put her on medication and told her to calm down.
她给数以万计的观众带来了艺术享受，
(Applause)
她也是个亿万富翁。可是，有人
What I think it comes to is this:
现在，我想说的是--（掌声）
Al Gore spoke the other night
AL Gore（注：美国前副总统） 曾在这里做过一次演讲
about ecology and the revolution that was triggered by Rachel Carson.
I believe our only hope for the future
我相信对于未来，我们的唯一出路
is to adopt a new conception of human ecology,
是贯彻一种新的人性化生态的思想，
one in which we start to reconstitute our conception
也就是说我们应重新定义
of the richness of human capacity.
Our education system has mined our minds
我们的教育体系培养我们的方式
in the way that we strip-mine the earth for a particular commodity.
And for the future, it won't serve us.
但这种方式对于未来将不再适用。
We have to rethink the fundamental principles
我们必须重新思考那些最基本的准则
on which we're educating our children.
There was a wonderful quote by Jonas Salk, who said,
Jonas Salk曾说过：“如果所有的昆虫
"If all the insects were to disappear from the Earth,
within 50 years, all life on Earth would end.
那么50年之内，所有生命也将从地球上消失。
If all human beings disappeared from the Earth,
而如果人类从地球上消失的话，
within 50 years, all forms of life would flourish."
那么50年之内，其他物种会活得更好。”
And he's right.
他说的很对。
What TED celebrates is the gift of the human imagination.
TED倡导的是人类的创造性思维。
We have to be careful now that we use this gift wisely,
现在，我们必须运用这种思维方式小心地
and that we avert some of the scenarios that we've talked about.
避开那些按部就班的规则
And the only way we'll do it is by seeing our creative capacities
就是运用创造力
for the richness they are
and seeing our children for the hope that they are.
最大限度地发挥创造力，而且
And our task is to educate their whole being,
用孩子们喜欢的方式培养他们。 我们的任务
so they can face this future.
是全方位地培养孩子， 这样他们才能面对未来的社会。
By the way -- we may not see this future,
顺便说句--我们可能活不到未来那天
but they will.
但孩子们会。而我们要做的就是帮助
And our job is to help them make something of it.
Thank you very much.
他们能在未来有所作为。谢谢大家。
(Applause)